<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bishop of Exons Caution to his diocese against false doctrines delivered in a sermon at Truro in Cornwall at his primary visitation.</title>
            <author>Sparrow, Anthony, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280832</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58708</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58708)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Bishop of Exons Caution to his diocese against false doctrines delivered in a sermon at Truro in Cornwall at his primary visitation.</title>
                  <author>Sparrow, Anthony, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Timothy Garthwait,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published in 1676 as pt. 2 of A rationale upon the Book of Common Prayer"--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58708:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58708:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Biſhop of EXONS CAUTION TO HIS DIOCESE <hi>Againſt Falſe Doctrines,</hi> Delivered in a SERMON AT <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RO</hi> in <hi>CORNWALL</hi> at his Primary Viſitation.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the Tower of Babel and the confusion of tongues</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>Confuſion of Tongues. <bibl>
                        <hi>Gen: ii. 7. 8</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Timothy Garthwait,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58708:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58708:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE DIOCESE.</head>
            <p>WHEN I ſee ſo many falſe Teachers ſubtilly inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves into the affections of the people, and buſily inticing them by many artifices, from the ſtedfaſtneſs of their faith, and Allegiance to God in his Anointed and his Church. The care of the <hi>Dioceſe</hi> committed to my charge, and the remembrance of the Account which I muſt give to God for your ſouls, ſets me not only to my prayers, but my study too, to prevent your ruine; And I know no better way to do it then by performing the <hi>Watchmans</hi> part, <hi>Ezek. 4.</hi> Giving you warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to avoid the temptations, and encouraging you to ſtand faſt in the Lord; and I could not finde any way to do that, but by making my advice ſo publick, that all who liſted might receive it. And becauſe that counſel and advice is moſt acceptable, when it is put into the dreſs of a Sermon; I reſolved to make uſe of that Method which was moſt likely to inſtill effectually this Caution. When I had determined this, I reſolved further to preſent it as ſhort and plain as might be, that it might be the more ſerviceable to thoſe who moſt needed it, thoſe namely who have leaſt time to read, and leaſt ability to underſtand: But withall I have indeavoured in this
<pb facs="tcp:58708:3"/> ſhort piece to deliver all neceſſary <hi>Cautions</hi> with as clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and demonſtration out of Scriptures, as I could. It was not poſſible for me to Caution againſt every particular Error or falſe doctrine ſpread amongſt you; there be ſo many that it would have required a volume, to recount and refute them, and few would have given themſelves the trouble to read ſo large a diſcourſe; nor was it neceſſary, for it is more eaſie, and as ſafe, to ſecure from the danger of all, by ſome general Rules and Preſcriptions, which if they be obſerved, will certainly preſerve you from all dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrines, and keep you ſtedfaſt in the holy Faith. I ſhall heartily deſire you to believe that this <hi>Caution</hi> is given you by him who loves you as his own ſoul and can with the greateſt ſincerity ſay of you, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> What is my hope or joy, or crown of rejoycing, are not even ye in the preſence of the Lord? Ye are our Glory and joy, if any of you ſhall draw back and fall from the ſtedfaſtneſs of the faith, my Soul ſhall have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in him, <hi>Heb. 10.38.</hi> But, <hi>Now I live if you ſtand faſt in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THere is lately publiſhed A <hi>RATIONALE</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58708:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Theſſal. 3.8.</bibl>
                  <p>Now we live, if you ſtand faſt in the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>PAUL</hi> having lately converted the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith, was call'd to preach the Goſpel in other parts; in this his neceſſary abſence, he ſtill retains a tender fatherly affection for his children. <hi>We being taken from you for a ſhort time, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the more abundantly to ſee your face with great deſire,</hi> chap. 2.17. <hi>Wherefore we would have come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you once and again, I</hi> Paul <hi>eſpecially, but Satan hindred us.</hi> He had put upon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a neceſſity of ſtaying where he was, to ſettle ſome unſeaſonable Diſputes and Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies with the <hi>Stoicks</hi> and <hi>Epicureans,</hi> rais'd by this great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Souls, on purpoſe to divert the bleſſed Apoſtle from his charitable deſign towards the <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> When St. <hi>Paul</hi> found himſelf thus hindred, he ſends <hi>Timothy</hi> with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, in his name, to Viſit his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> to ſtabliſh his new Converts, to comfort them, and to know their faith, <hi>leſt by ſome means the Tempter hath tempted you, and our labor be in vain,</hi> verſe 5. When <hi>Timothy</hi> had finiſh'd his Viſitation he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to give an account of his Enquiries and proceedings, and brought this good tidings, that he had found the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> firm and ſtedfaſt in the Faith which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had taught them; at the hearing of this good report, St. <hi>Paul</hi> breaks out into this Rhetorical expreſſion of his joy and contentment in the Meſſage, <hi>Now we live,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58708:4"/>
               <p>I AM come hither on the very ſame errand, to know your Faith; and though I cannot but hope, that after ſo long profeſſion of the holy Faith, ye are well rooted and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, yet I cannot but know that there are amongſt us many buſie and cunning Tempters, who uſe various and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile arts to withdraw you from the holy Faith; and I have reaſon to fear, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, leſt by ſome means the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath prevailed upon ſome; and therefore could no longer forbear to come and know your Faith, and if I ſhall find you like theſe <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſtrong and ſtedfaſt therein, I ſhall ſay with the ſame ſincerity that the Apoſtle did, <hi>Now I live if you ſtand faſt in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND that you may continue conſtant and ſtedfaſt in the holy Faith which our Lord hath delivered, I ſhall briefly and plainly ſet before you ſuch rules and directions out of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>ancient</hi> Writers, as by Gods aſſiſtance upon your hearty prayers, ſhall undoubtedly preſerve you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>I. <hi>RULE,</hi> Is to make a ſerious and hearty <hi>Reſolution of Believing</hi> and <hi>adhering</hi> to this Chriſtian Faith, <hi>whatſoever it may coſt.</hi> This is that which our Saviour adviſes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.28. <hi>Which of you intending to build a towre, ſits not down firſt and counteth the coſt, whether he hath ſufficient to finiſh it, leſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finiſh it, all that behold him, begin to mock him.</hi> It will be no leſs ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous for any man to profeſs himſelf a Diſciple of Chriſt and his holy doctrine, that doth not firſt conſider the coſt he may be at, and reſolve to go on with it. And the coſt may be great, the loſs of Father and mother, and whatſoever is neareſt and deareſt to us. <hi>Verſe</hi> 26. <hi>If any man come to me and hates not his father and mother, and wife and children, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters, yea and his own life alſo, He cannot be my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> he cannot be ſtedfaſt in the Profeſſion of the holy Faith, which may and ſometimes will put him upon this coſt. Let no man ſo far miſtake our Lord, as to think that he teaches
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58708:4"/> diſobedience to Parents, whoſe firſt commandment with promiſe, is, <hi>Honor thy father and mother;</hi> or that he teaches us to hate our children, who by his Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that they are worſe than Infidels, who provide not for their family, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. or that he teaches us to hate our ſelves, who hath ſummed up his Commandments into theſe two grand precepts, <hi>Love God above all, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.40. St. <hi>Lukes</hi> phraſe of hating father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is beſt expounded by St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that loves father and mother more than me.</hi> He that prefers father and mother more than me and my doctrine, and will renounce that or any part of it to ſave them or his own life, and whatſoever is deareſt to him in this world, is not worthy of me. The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Reſolution of preferring God and his holy Truth before all worldly advantages, is that which makes the honeſt and good heart, which affords depth of earth for the Seed of Gods Word to root in, and bring forth fruit to life eternal, St. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.15. Let us therefore retire to our cloſets and frequently renew this honeſt purpoſe and reſolution, eſpecially when we come to the holy <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that we may get it ſeal'd and confirmed there by the Grace of the holy Spirit; let not the coſt we may be at affright us; the rich pearl of the holy Faith (the end of which is the ſalvation of our ſouls, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9.) is not dearly bought, though we ſell all that we have to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it, St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.46.</p>
               <p>THIS reſolution will not continue ſtedfaſt, unleſs we purge out of our hearts all ſuch violent <hi>luſts</hi> and <hi>paſſions,</hi> as will raviſh our Wills from the holy Faith which we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; let us therefore be careful to caſt out them, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe which are moſt dangerous to the ſtedfaſtneſs of the Faith. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. THE <hi>inordinate love</hi> of this preſent world, this made <hi>Demas</hi> forſake St. <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had been a long time his fellow-laborer in the preaching of the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58708:5"/> There be too many ſuch, who follow Chriſts doctrine for gain, who make great profeſſion of this holy Faith, when it fills their baskets, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.14. who run away from it as faſt, to any impertinent, nay damnable Error which appears more advantageous; if we have hearts exerciſed with covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, we ſhall certainly forſake the right way as <hi>Balaam</hi> did for the wages of unrighteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>AMBITION</hi> and Vain-glory, <hi>Diotrephes</hi> who loves to have the pre-eminence, receives not the Apoſtles nor their doctrine, <hi>Jo.</hi> ep. 3. Nay ſlights their doctrine, vilifies their perſons, prating againſt them with malicious words, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. and all this, to get himſelf a name and eſteem amongſt the credulous vulgar. This hath made moſt of the Hereticks and Schiſmaticks in elder times, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and others have obſerved; when they thought their worth and merit not enough rewarded, when they could not be ſo great or power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as they affected to be; when they could not obtain by the regular and juſt wayes of preferment, ſuch places and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſuch eſteem and repute, as their ambition made them covet, and think themſelves to have deſerved; then they broacht new Doctrines, and invented new Diſciplines to draw parties after them of the weaker ſort, that they might be in a <hi>Faction,</hi> what they could not be in the <hi>Church,</hi> Chiefs and Leaders. Nor doth this Ambition appear only in the Leaders, but every little member of the moſt ridiculous Sect is ſwoln with the ſame tumorous vain-glory, each party af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting to be call'd the Godly. Where this winde of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion blows, no wonder if it carries them away to divers and ſtrange doctrines, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9. How can ye believe, receiving or catching at Glory one of another, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.44. When the Teachers court the people, and they again the Teachers for applauſe and reputation, when vain-glory is the end of the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ign, how can men be ſtedfaſt? for when the holy Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, as oftentimes it does, vile and contemptible in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58708:5"/> eyes of the people, ſuch men muſt needs forſake it, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs any new, though damnable doctrine, that grows popular. Beſides, no man can hope to ſtand ſtedfaſt in the Faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aſſiſtance of Gods grace, who reſiſts the proud and gives his grace only to the Humble, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6. if we will be conſtant Diſciples of Chriſt we muſt be like him, lowly in Spirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. THERE is in our nature a <hi>ſoftneſs</hi> or tenderneſs that is apt to betray our conſtancy. As many as deſire to make a fair ſhew in the fleſh, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with a fair face without a skar, renounce their Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and turn Jews; <hi>only leſt they ſhould ſuffer perſecution for the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 6.12. This tenderneſs made the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and all, once forſake their Lord; and the ſame hath made too many forſake the Lords holy Truth. It may not perhaps be thought needful to urge this any further at this time, when God be thankt, there is no preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuffering perſecution for the Faith of Chriſt, it being now defended by the <hi>Defender of the Faith;</hi> but though Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Faith and Doctrine of our Lord be not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the ſword of Authority, it is, at leaſt ſome part of it, curſtly perſecuted by the ſpears and arrows, and ſharp ſwords of ſlanderous tongues, who like the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old, cry out of perſecution, even then when they are thus ſharply perſecuting thoſe who profeſs and preach the holy Truth and Faith of Chriſt. To inſtance in a few particulars, let any man preach or practiſe Decency and <hi>Order</hi> in the Service and Worſhip of God, which is a direct command in Chriſts holy Doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.10. Let him preach or practiſe Loyalty and <hi>Obedience</hi> to the King and his <hi>Laws,</hi> which is part of the ſame holy doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. Let him preach or practiſe obedience to the <hi>Church,</hi> according to our Lords direction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. And ſubmiſſion to the guidance of thoſe, who by God and mans Laws are ſet over
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58708:6"/> us to watch for our Souls, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. and he ſhall ſoon find the truth of that which I have ſaid, his doctrine ſlandered, and his perſon reproached and perſecuted by malicious tongues. The fear of this perſecution we ſee, hath made ſome, who are too tender, follow our Lords doctrine as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did his Maſter, at a diſtance; it is not amiſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, what the Holy Ghoſt hath obſerved for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that ſoon after he drew back and followed at a diſtance, he forſook, nay forſwore his Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.58,74. from all which we may certainly conclude, that we ſhall never ſtand ſtedfaſt in the Doctrine and Faith of our Lord, unleſs we indeavour to harden our faces and ſtrengthen our foreheads againſt all ſuch fear of the looks or tongues of men, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.8,9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. AS there is a tenderneſs, ſo there is a <hi>fickleneſs</hi> and love of change in our corrupted nature; St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhneſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. loving much but not long, delighting in change, not only in ordinary matters, dreſſes and faſhions, but even in Religion too; new Prayers, new Doctrines, new Governments; many men having itching ears, heap to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Teachers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. after their own luſts, ſuch as may rub their ears, and gratifie their luſts and ſeveral hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, with doctrines ſuitable, and pleaſe their childiſhneſs with novelties; new Revelations, new Truths are by many much affected and daily expected: I pray God we come not to the Jews Innovation, <hi>New Gods</hi> which our Fathers never heard of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.17. We ſeem weary of the old garment, the old Religion, and love to put new peices to it, though thereby we make it much worſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.36. Nothing can be more directly oppoſite to our ſtedfaſtneſs in the Truth, then this love of change; ſince the holy Faith and Chriſtian truth is like Jeſus Chriſt who taught it, the ſame yeſterday and to day, the ſame for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Let us labor therefore to correct this childiſhneſs, to quit our ſelves like
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58708:6"/> men, and earneſtly contend for that Faith which was once and but once delivered, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. By the means aforeſaid we may, by Gods grace, ſecure our ſelves againſt our ſelves, that our own hearts ſhall not miſlead us; but though our hearts be ſincere, our underſtandings may be weak, and we may be daily in danger of being ſeduced by the various arts and ſubtilties of cunning and buſie ſeducers, who lie in wait to deceive; and therefore I ſhall offer this <hi>SECOND Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which our bleſſed Lord hath taught us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>II. BEWARE of falſe Prophets or <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and you will readily grant the Caution to be moſt ſeaſonable and neceſſary, if you will conſider, the <hi>Crafts</hi> they uſe to deceive you, and your own dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger if you be deceived; inwardly, ſaies our Saviour, they are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Wolves, whoſe aim and deſign, is no leſs then the ruine and damnation of your ſouls. What danger can be greater? This cruel and malicious deſign they hide and cover under Sheeps clothing, ſoft and fair pretences of meekneſs and humility, profeſſors of extraordinary holineſs, great care of ſouls, ſingular love of Gods glory, to which they add good words; kind and flattering ſpeeches, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18. and (which is the maſter piece of cunning) they promiſe them liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Simon Magus, Baſilides, Carpocrates</hi> of old, taught their Diſciples to live as they liſted, and to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they pleaſed; <hi>Marcion</hi> taught his Diſciples to believe that Chriſt came into the world to deliver men from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Creator; <hi>Meletius</hi> gave his followers a licence to live without fear, and to be rul'd and govern'd by none. I might inſtance in many more ſuch falſe teachers of the ſame leaven, but I need not, ſince St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the place aforeſaid, aſſures us, that it is the wont of falſe Teachers of what ſort ſoever, to promiſe their followers liberty; this ſweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of liberty, or rather licenciouſneſs being the moſt catching argument in the world to entice itching ears and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58708:7"/> luſtful hearts to their party. It is not unworthy of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaies they <hi>promiſe</hi> them liberty, but indeed, they neither do nor can, by theſe means make them free, for whoſoever committeth ſin, is the ſervant of ſin. What liberty then can it be, to be expoſed and tempted to the deadly ſlavery of Error and ſin?</p>
               <p>FALSE Teachers having all of them ſuch malicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of ruine and ſuch cunning artifices to deceive; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us very much to remember our Lords Caution, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi> But how ſhall we diſcern them to be ſuch? Their inward deſigns we cannot ſee, and their outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance is innocent and harmleſs, fair and plauſible, ſheeps clothing, <hi>By their fruits you ſhall know them,</hi> ſaies our Saviour; they may act the ſheep for a while, but if you heed and mark them well, you ſhall ſee the Wolf appear, <hi>by their fruits you ſhall know them.</hi> When you ſee ſome creeping into houſes, and inſtilling doctrines into the weaker ſort; by this you have juſt cauſe to ſuſpect them for falſe Teachers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, from ſuch turn away. There ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſhall bring in damnable doctrines, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. when they who offer themſelves to be your Teachers, ſhall forſake the lawful and publick aſſemblies eſtabliſhed by juſt authority in the houſes of prayer, by this fruit you may know them. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved remember the words which were ſpoken before of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> How that they told you there ſhould be in the laſt time Mockers or Deceivers, <hi>Jude</hi> 17, 18. Theſe be they who ſeparate themſelves; beware of ſuch therefore, by theſe fruits you ſhall juſtly ſuſpect them to be falſe Teachers; but there is one Character or mark by which you ſhall undoubtedly know them, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Jude,</hi> and all tell us for certain, thoſe are falſe Teachers, by all means to be avoided, who deſpiſe Government, and ſpeak evil of dignities; when therefore you hear any Teachers blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58708:7"/> and reviling their Governors Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, when you ſee them contemning their Laws, confronting their Authority, refuſing to come at <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> call, to the Aſſemblies appointed by their Laws; and ſetting up Meetings, gathering aſſemblies againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical authority; come not neer, leſt ye periſh in their ſin, <hi>Num.</hi> 16. It is Gods own caution there, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. and in the like caſe too, for what elſe was the ſin of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> but refuſing to come at the call of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Num. 16.12. <hi>We will not come up;</hi> and the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Congregations againſt them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. And certainly to gather Congregations contrary to the Laws and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> is to gather againſt <hi>THEM,</hi> for it is the Authority that makes the King and the Prieſt; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſo ſacred that no man muſt riſe againſt them, when therefore you ſee or hear any ſo gathering Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions contrary to the Laws; Depart from them; when you hear any Teachers thus deſpiſing Dominion, remember that the Apoſtles have told us, they are falſe Teachers, and forget not our Lords own Caution, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets;</hi> if any man after all this monition will ſtill be bold to receive ſuch, becauſe they come in ſheeps clothing, he deſerves more blame then pitty, if he be ruined and devoured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>III. OBEY your ſpiritual <hi>Guides,</hi> and ſubmit your ſelves to their conduct and direction, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. This Rule is given us to this very purpoſe, that we may ſtand faſt in the faith. For after the Apoſtle had forewarned us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>Be not carried about with diverſe and ſtrange doctrines;</hi> he preſcribes this as the beſt prevention of ſuch giddineſs and lightneſs to obey them that have the Rule over us, and ſubmit our ſelves to them who watch for our ſouls. Almighty God in infinite goodneſs to man, knowing the weakneſs of the peoples un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, together with the want of time and means for the ſtudy of Truth, hath provided ſome Paſtors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58708:8"/> for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. <hi>That we henceforth be no more children, toſs'd to and fro, and carried about with every winde of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craftineſs of men, whereby they lie in wait to deceive,</hi> Verſ. 14. God hath you ſee appointed you Paſtors and Teachers to keep you from being deceived by falſe Teachers, and if you will not ſubmit to their direction, you expoſe your ſelves to the danger of being deceived, and fruſtrate the merciful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of Gods goodneſs towards you, to keep you ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the Truth. I know not what excuſe any man can make why he doth not readily ſubmit to the guidance of theſe Paſtors and Teachers, but only this, <hi>That firſt he does not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know whom Chriſt hath appointed for his Guides now, ſince the Apoſtles themſelves are dead long ſince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND if he does know them, yet he cannot confidently relie upon their guidance, ſince they are not infallible in their doctrines, as the Apoſtles were, and therefore may poſſibly be deceived them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and deceive him that ſubmits to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TO the firſt I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. YOU may as certainly know who are your Spiritual Guides, as who are your Civil Governors; namely by the Laws of Church and Kingdom, and their ſolemn Inveſtiture in their ſeveral places and charges; Which is a greater and ſurer evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence then any man can have of his natural Parent, whom you cannot otherwiſe know then by the common repute of the neighbourhood, and the Teſtimony of your Mother, who is bound in reputation to call her own husband your father; ſince God hath commanded you, upon pain of damnation to obey him, who is thus reputed your Father; why ſhould you not fear the ſame penalty for diſobeying your Guides of ſouls, whom God hath equally commanded you to obey, and given you a greater evidence and aſſurance of their authority over you.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58708:8"/>
               <p>TO the ſecond ſcruple I anſwer, that I aſſert no <hi>Infallibility</hi> in your Spiritual Guides. They are men, and may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, they may be cunning men and lie in wait to deceive. And may not thoſe be ſuch, whom you heap to your ſelves, and ſo willingly run after? Thoſe who are ſet over you, are <hi>reſtrain'd</hi> by the <hi>Laws,</hi> and accountable to their Superiors, ſo that they cannot publiſh dangerous Errors without their own danger and the cenſures of the Laws, if they be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and being allowed to preach <hi>only</hi> in the Church, cannot promiſe themſelves any ſafety from ſecrecy. And it is not ſo probable that they will willingly deceive you, who are in danger to loſe by their fraud, as they who by falſe doctrines make parties to their no ſmall advantage. Beſides, God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>aſſiſts</hi> his own Inſtitutions, and bleſſes his own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. God hath forewarned you to avoid ſtrangers, to heap to your ſelves Teachers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. and who can reaſonably expect Gods aſſiſtance in Diſobedience? It is juſt with him to ſuffer us to be deceived by thoſe whom he hath warned us to avoid; but it is moſt reaſonable to expect his bleſſing and aſſiſtance in obedience to his own order. He hath commanded us to ſubmit to them who are ſet over us, and will not ſuffer us to periſh by obedience; If we ſhall be miſlead by our own Guides into ſmall Errors, he will graciouſly accept our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and not impute thoſe Errors to our condemnation; and he will never ſuffer us to be led by them into damnable Errors, unleſs it be our own fault, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above that you are able to bear, but with the Temptation will make way to eſcape;</hi> This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe would fail, if having commanded us to be guided by them, he ſhould not, either certainly withhold them from Teaching Damnable doctrines, or elſe afford us ſome means for the avoidance and diſcovery, if we be watchful, and not willfully refuſe them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. OBSERVE this Rule of our Saviour, S. <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58708:9"/> the Scriptures,</hi> acquaint your ſelves with the <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>evident texts</hi> which need no interpretation, and if your Teachers commend any doctrine to you contrary to thoſe, believe them not. It is an old obſervation and daily experience confirms it, that falſe Teachers uſe to build their doctrines upon ſome few hard and obſcure texts, that under the colour of the holy text they may obtrude upon their unwary Diſciples, their own pernicious Gloſſes, Interpretations and inferences; ſo that their diſciples belief reſts only upon the Interpretation of the preacher who may be deceived, or which is worſe, may indeavor to deceive; but when the ſober and wary Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an grounds his belief upon the evident Texts which are ſo plain that they cannot be more plainly expreſſed or interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he relies undoubtedly upon Gods own word who cannot deceive or be deceived. This is the beſt way to ſecure our ſelves againſt the damnable doctrines of your own falſe Teachers; as for example, when you are by any of them taught to rebel againſt the King, or to oppoſe his Laws, to contemn the Church, and ſeparate from her Communion; <hi>Guard</hi> your faith againſt their crafty inſinuations of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by pretence of obſcure Scriptures, by ſuch plain Texts as theſe, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> to him that bears the fword not only for wrath but alſo for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, and whoſoever reſiſts ſhall receive damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Be ſubject to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governors, who are ſent by him,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. which are words as plain as can be ſpoken, and cannot admit of any other interpretation. Theſe are enough to ſecure you againſt the damnable doctrine of Rebellion, and againſt contempt of the Church and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical ſeparation from her Communion; take theſe plain Texts, St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. He that will not hear the Church, let him be to thee as an Heathen man and Publican. <hi>Keep the unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> Eph. 4.3. <hi>Not forſaking the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58708:9"/> publick aſſembling of our ſelves,</hi> Heb. 10.25. according to the commands of thoſe who are our Governors, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</p>
               <p>IF it be <hi>objected</hi> that all theſe Texts do ſuppoſe the Kings and the Churches commands to be lawful, otherwiſe I may, nay I muſt refuſe to obey the King, I muſt not hear the Church, I muſt forſake thoſe Aſſemblies if unlawful. The <hi>anſwer</hi> is eaſie, That I cannot be ſafe in going contrary to theſe plain texts, till I can find, that thoſe particular Commands of my Superiors, and thoſe Aſſemblies, be <hi>as plainly forbidden</hi> in ſome other Texts; It is not ſafe to ſay, I will not obey the the King, nor hearken to the Church, nor frequent thoſe publick Aſſemblies, becauſe I think, and ſome powerful Preachers tell me, theſe ordinances and Aſſemblies are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
               <p>REMEMBER, it is God who commands in thoſe plain Texts before mentioned, and none but himſelf can diſcharge my obedience, and therefore you muſt obey till you find the particular commands of your Superiors forbidden by as <hi>plain</hi> Texts, as thoſe which in general require you to obey. If you obſerve this rule, you cannot be cheated into Rebellion and Schiſm, and if you do not, it is your own fault, that you are deceived.</p>
               <p>THIS Rule is certain, but perhaps not large enough to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from all <hi>damnable</hi> Errors, there being ſome ſuch, which may not ſeem flat contrary to the expreſs words of Scripture; the neceſſary Truths of which thoſe errors are deſtructive, not being delivered in expreſs terms in the holy Scriptures, yet ſufficiently contained therein, and may be undoubtedly proved out of them by comparing of Texts, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the context, and ſcope of the Text, and other rules of Art; Which the people not being ſo well able to do, let them obſerve this ſecond rule.</p>
               <p n="2">2. KEEP ſtedfaſt in the <hi>Faith</hi> of all ſuch Truths as the <hi>Catholick</hi> Apoſtolick Church hath <hi>believed</hi> and <hi>delivered</hi> as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58708:10"/> 
                  <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and believe not your <hi>particular</hi> Guide, when he teaches contrary to theſe. The Church is the ground and pillar of Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. into her boſome and Regiſtry, the Apoſtles committed all neceſſary Truths as our Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19,20. Go teach all Nations to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, they knew their Lords Commands and were true to their truſt in teaching them accordingly. Theſe neceſſary truths thus laid up in the Treaſury of the Church are Domeſtick hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold doctrines, which all of that Family ſhould hold faſt, and not be carried about with every winde of ſtrange or forein doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9. Theſe neceſſary truths, committed by the Apoſtles to the Churches of their own plantation, God hath promiſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. ſhould be delivered down through all ſucceſſion to the end of the world, <hi>Lo I am with you</hi> (namely in the teaching all that I have commanded) <hi>to the end of the world.</hi> What therefore hath been conſtantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and believed as commands of Chriſt, by the <hi>general Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>univerſal Church</hi> in all ages, ought to be firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed; upon the ſame conſentient Teſtimony we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and believe the <hi>Canonical Scriptures</hi> to be the word of God, and why ſhould we not be ſatisfied with the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of all other neceſſary Truths? <hi>But how ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be able to know which Truths are ſo generally delivered from the firſt ages till now;</hi> they cannot themſelves ſearch and finde them, and perhaps their own Teachers may tell them that their Errors are ſuch.</p>
               <p>I ANSWER, you may finde and know theſe neceſſary truths, <hi>by the publick doctrine of our own Church, delivered in her Liturgy</hi> and Articles <hi>of Religion,</hi> by the unanimous conſent of <hi>all your ſpiritual Guides.</hi> Acquaint your ſelves throughly with that publick doctrine and adhere to that, and if your own Teacher teach otherwiſe, believe him not. If to theſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions here given, you carefully attend, adding your conſtant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58708:10"/> humble <hi>prayers</hi> to that Merciful God who would have no man to periſh, but that all ſhould come to the knowledge of the Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. He will certainly preſerve you from all damnable Errors, and keep you ſtedfaſt in the holy Faith; That faith which is the ground and foundation of the lively hope of <hi>an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not away, reſerved in Heaven for you,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3,4. that Faith by which through the power of God ye are kept unto Salvation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. that faith, which being preſerv'd firm and ſtedfaſt, after it hath been tried by manifold temptations will be found unto Praiſe, and Honour, and Glory at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6, 7. That faith which makes us here in this life to rejoyce with joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. and in the end brings us to the ſalvation of our ſouls, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. which God of his infinite mercy grant us all, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt be all honour and Glory, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
